[Music]
let's see a geometric way to find this
infinite sum
start with a positive real number X
that's less than one then draw a square
with side length given by the infinite
sum of the powers of X in particular the
side length can be decomposed into a
bunch of line segments of length 1 x x
squared x cubed x to the fourth and so
on
applying the sum formula for an infinite
convergent geometric series we see that
the side length of this Square must be
one over one minus X
now we can use the labeled side lengths
to decompose the square into a bunch of
rectangles first in the lower left
corner we have a one by one square with
area one next to that we have two x by 1
rectangles both containing area X so
together they enclose an area of 2x
on top of those two rectangles we can
shade in a 1 by x squared rectangle and
X by X rectangle and an x squared by one
rectangle
together these three rectangles enclose
an area of 3x squared on top of those
rectangles we can place four rectangles
each with area X cubed and closing an
area of 4X Cubed on top of those
rectangles we have five rectangles each
enclosing an area of x to the fourth for
a total area of five x to the fourth and
then we have these six rectangles
enclosing a total area of 6X to the
fifth
we can continue this process
indefinitely each time we add n
rectangles each enclosing an area of x
to the N minus one but now we can
imagine that this process has been
carried out infinitely often that means
that we're looking at a limiting process
in this infinite limiting process the
entire Square will be shaded by these
rectangles that means that the infinite
sum that we're thinking about must equal
the area of the square but the area of
this Square can be computed just by
taking the product of the two side
lengths which are both one over one
minus X
therefore the infinite sum where n
ranges from 1 to Infinity of n times x
to the N minus 1 must equal the quantity
one over one minus x squared and this is
in fact the formula for the sum of the
differentiated geometric series